

Vlas Sokolov Astrophysics Ph.D.

i 24 April 1991, Ukraine

Munich, Germany

vsokolov@mpe.mpg.de

(+49/0) 174 83 22 851

vlas-sokolov.github.io

GitHub profile: vlas-sokolov

Stack Overflow: profile link

About me —

As a Ph.D. candidate in astrophysics, I am conducting academical research and performing data analysis on large astronomical datasets, using modern Python data analysis tools and a deep understanding of statistical methods. In particular, I am building data reduction pipelines, routinely performing non-linear regression analysis and model selection for imaging and spectroscopic data, and extensively use various visualization tools to communicate the scientific results obtained.

Skills ———

ADVANCED (6+ YEARS): Scientific Python (numpy, scipy, pandas, matplotlib), UNIX-like OS

INTERMEDIATE (2+ YEARS): bash, git, scikit-learn, LaTeX

Familiar (up to 1 year): C/C++, R, matlab, Open MPI

Languages ———

English (fluent); German, Chinese (intermediate); Ukranian, Russian (native)

Work Experience —

2014-current Max Planck Institute for Extraterrestrial Physics Research Assistant Conducting academic research and analysing astronomical observations of the early stages of massive star formation.

2012-2014 National Tsing Hua University

Research Assistant

- Establishing an evolutionary sequence of massive protostars (Python)
- Wrote a Levenberg-Marquardt algorithm implementation (C)
- Teaching Assistant for PHYS 4330 (2013 Spring and Fall semesters)

Education —

| Sep 2014 – Jul 2018 (expected) | Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München Ph.D. candidate in Astrophysics | Germany |
|-----------------------------------|--|---------|
| Sep 2012 – Aug 2014 | National Tsing Hua University M.Sc.; Institute of Astronomy | Taiwan |
| Sep 2008 – Jul 2012 | National Chiao Tung University B.Sc.; Dept. of Electrophysics | Taiwan |
| Sep 2004 – Jun 2008 | Kyiv Natural Science Lyceum | Ukraine |

Relevant Online Courses ———

| 2018-; \sim 3 months | Deep Learning | (Udacity, ongoing) |
|------------------------|-----------------------------|--------------------|
| 2018; 10 weeks | Intro to Machine Learning | (Udacity) |
| 2013; 4 weeks | Computing for Data Analysis | (Coursera) |

Technical Expertise ——

- Extensive hands-on experience in processing noisy imaging and spectral data
- Grid-search optimization for initial values of a gradient descent-like algorithm (Python; GitHub link)
- Bayesian inference and model selection package for large spectroscopic datasets (Python, nested sampling, Open MPI; GitHub link)
- Webscraper for an automated retrieval of Herschel infrared Galactic Plane Survey data (Python, selenium; GitHub link)
- Co-author on a multivariate clustering method for astrophysical applications (Python, in prep.)
- Co-author on a nonlinear regression package for astrophysical spectral lines (Python, in prep.)
- Active use of git-, Slack-, and jupiter workflows; Linux user for over a decade
- Alphabetical photo sorting by EXIF creation date (Python; on GitHub gist)

Academic Expertise —————

- Experience in independent academic research (list of publications)
- Talks at multiple international conferences
- Deep understanding of statistical methods and concepts
- Capacity for independent analysis and self-reliant problem-solving skills
- Keen interest in Bayesian parameter estimation and model comparison